Francis Hopkinson Smith Collection
Francis Hopkinson Smith Collection
1883-1915
Smith, Francis Hopkinson, 1838-1915
.25 linear ft.
25 outgoing letters, 4 incoming letters from William Henry Rideing; single typescript pages, with revisions, from 3 of Smith’s novels; and miscellany, including clipped signatures, an inscribed reproduction of a photographic portrait of F. Hopkinson Smith, and printed ephemera, including booksellers’ catalogs and an advertisement.
149653
Biographical History
American author, illustrator, and novelist.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1883 to 1915, the Francis Hopkinson Smith Collection comprises correspondence, writings and miscellany pertaining to the American author and illustrator (1838-1915). Correspondence includes 25 outgoing Smith letters and 4 incoming items from William Henry Rideing of The Youth's Companion. Four of the letters document an escalating dispute between Smith and agent Major James B. Pond concerning lecture fees. Writings include single typescript pages with extensive holograph revisions of three of Smith's novels, together with a published story bearing his signature. (The manuscript pages originally may have been enclosures with a 1903 Oct 23 letter to James Carlton Young.) Clipped signatures, an inscribed reproduction of a photographic portrait, and printed ephemera, including a periodical issue containing a tribute to F. Hopkinson Smith, booksellers' catalogues, and an advertisement, constitute Miscellany.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Literature -- American Fiction; Doane, William Croswell, 1832-1913; Kobbé, Gustav, 1857-1918; Pond, James B. (James Burton), 1838-1903; Rideing, William H. (William Henry), 1853-1918; Smith, Francis Hopkinson, 1838-1915, Correspondence; Young, James Carleton, 1856-1918; Art, American.; Authors, American; Illustrators, United States; Novelists, American; Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Artists.; Authors.; Illustrators.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Linda Squair, 1994.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing (Box 1)
  - Incoming (Box 1)
- Writing
  - Caleb West, 1 p. typescript with holograph revisions, inscribed (Box 1)
  - Oliver Horn, 1 p. typescript with holograph revisions, inscribed (Box 1)
  - Tom Grogan, 1 p. typescript with holograph revisions, inscribed (Box 1)
  - "The Professor on 'How to Train Our Wives and Children' ", published story, signed by F. Hopkinson Smith (Box 1)
- Miscellany
  - Bookseller's advertisement for Caleb West Master Diver by F. Hopkinson Smith (Oversize 1)
  - Catalogue (1897-98) - Central Lyceum Bureau - lists F. Hopkinson Smith as lecturer (p. 15) (Box 1)
  - "Catalogue of First Editions, Autographs" (1912) - James F. Drake - lists F. Hopkinson Smith (p. 15) (Box 1)
  - "List of Holiday Books" (Dec. 1903) - H. H. Otis & Sons - contains reproduction of F. Hopkinson Smith photograph (p. 13) (Box 1)
  - Pamphlet (1891) - Egypt Exploration Fund - lists Mrs. F. Hopkinson Smith among local honorary secretaries (last page) (Box 1)
  - Periodical issue (21 Apr 1915) The Outlook - contains tribute to F. Hopkinson Smith upon his death (p. 910) (Box 1)
  - Reproduction of a photograph of F. Hopkinson Smith (Box 1)
  - Reproduction of a photographic portrait of F. Hopkinson Smith, inscribed and bearing date Mar. 1913 (Box 1)
  - Signatures (2) of F. Hopkinson Smith (with presentation letters) (Box 1)